Guide to the British Correspondence and Miscellany Collection, 1556-1972 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
British Correspondence and Miscellany collection 1556-1972 and undated
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
4.0 linear feet Extent: 3,500 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00151
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The British Correspondence and Miscellany Collection was acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1966 to 1986 from a variety of sources.
Collection Overview
The materials comprising the British Correspondence and Miscellany Collection are dated from 1556 to 1972 (bulk 1740-1890). The papers are arranged into the following series: Correspondence, 1556-1972 and undated; Subject Files, 1699-1902 and undated; Pictures, 1795-1921 and undated; and Miscellaneous Material, 1814-1836 and undated An artificial collection, the papers are, for the most part, unrelated by provenance. The collection consists chiefly of correspondence, and topics include numerous political events and activities of the 18th, 19th, and early 20th centuries in Great Britain and the colonies (particularly India and Africa).
The Correspondence Series includes numerous letters to and from British notables. Among the major correspondents represented are: the 8th Duke of Argyll, the 1st and 2nd Barons Auckland, Charles Bradlaugh, John Bright; Robert Brownrigg; George Canning, John Wilson Croker, the 1st Earl of Durham, John Foster, the 1st Baron Dover, George Joachim Goschen, John Hay, the 3rd Marquess Lansdowne, W.E.H. Lecky, Captain John Lenty, the 1st Earl of Liverpool, the 3rd Earl of Lucan, William Melbourne, Lord Broderick Midleton, Viscount Milner, David Christie Murray, Thomas Nimmo, Baron Northcote, Pierce O'Mahoney, the 3rd Viscount Palmerston, the 1st Baronet Pollock, George Rose, the 7th Earl of Shaftesbury, William Sheowring, John Deas Thompson, the 1st Duke of Wellington, William Wilberforce, and Edward Wodehouse.
Among the items in the Correspondence Series are a copy of John Bright's 1851 speech entitled Papal Aggression (Bright correspondence); material regarding the Horseguards (Brownrigg correspondence); a testimonial to the character of Sir Francis Burdett written by Lady Hester Stanhope (Burdett correspondence); a letter regarding Wellington's correspondence concerning a transport ship wrecked in the Tagus during his last Iberian campaign (Canning correspondence); letters from David Dundas, including two accompanying circulars (1804 and 1805) from the War Office (Dundas correspondence); and correspondence (and accompanying transcripts) between King George I and M. Braconnier (1709) concerning the King's inability to send a detachment large enough to oppose the French along the borders of the Rhone and Lake Geneva (George I correspondence). Other items include correspondence relating to George Henry's mission in Nyasaland (Henry correspondence); material concerning the cargo ship The Sea Witch (Lenty correspondence); correspondence regarding Marsden-Smedley's unsuccessful campaign for Parliament in 1910 (Marsden-Smedley correspondence); and Wellesley's transcript of a testimonial to the character of Charles Wyatt written by the Governor General of India (Wellesley correspondence). The Murray correspondence includes handwritten biographical notes and a printed review (1908) of David Christie Murray's Reflections.
Papers in the Subject Files Series concern a wide range of political, military, and economic matters. They include an anonymous account (1743) of the battle of Dettingen (in French); papers (1856-1860 and undated) relating to the raising of ships at Sebastopol during the Crimean War; a collection of letters from various correspondents concerning decimal currency (1856-1869); papers concerning Newfoundland fisheries (1901-1902); and a document pertaining to the impressment of sailors (1745).
Subject Headings
Great Britain -- History; Great Britain -- Politics and government; Argyll, George Douglas Campbell, Duke of, 1823-1900; Bradlaugh, Charles, 1833-1891; Bright, John, 1811-1889; Brownrigg, Robert, 1759-1833; Canning, George, 1770-1827; Croker, John Wilson, 1780-1857; Durham, John George Lambton, Earl of, 1792-1840; Lansdowne, Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, Marquess of, 1780-1863; Lenty, John, Captain; Liverpool, Charles Cecil Cope Jenkinson, Earl of, 1784-1851; Lucan, George Charles Bingham, Earl of, 1800-1888; Midleton, William St. John Fremantle Brodrick, Earl of, b. 1856; Milner, Alfred Milner, Viscount, 1854-1925; Murray, David Christie, 1847-1907; Nimmo, Thomas; Iddesleigh, Stafford Henry Northcote, Earl of, 1621-1683; O'Mahony, Peirce Charles de Lacy, 1850-; Palmerston, Henry John Temple, Viscount, 1784-1865; Pollock, George, Sir, 1786-1872; Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1621-1683; Wellesley, Richard Wellesley, Marquess, 1760-1842; Wilberforce, William, 1759-1833; Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1556-1972 and undated
  This series includes letters to and from numerous British notables concerning political events spanning five centuries. Letters are arranged alphabetically by author. When the author could not be ascertained, the letter was filed under the name of the recipient, and this was noted in the finding aid. Letters of titled persons are filed under the title rather than the surname when the title could be determined. In some cases, this was not possible. Researchers are advised to search for correspondence of particular people under both title and surname. In cases where there are several letters by one author, the letters were placed in a folder with that author's name and filed at the end of the folders beginning with that letter of the alphabet. (Example: After the alphabetically arranged A letters, there are folders containing letters by George Douglas Campbell, the 8th Duke of Argyll, and William George Eden, the 2nd Baron Auckland.). Unidentified letters appear at the end of the alphabetical range.
  - Abbas - Azikiwe, 1799-1961 and undated (Box 1)
    - Abbas, Ferhat (Box 1)
    - Abbott, Charles (Box 1)
    - Aberdare, Henry Austin, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Aberdeen, G.H. Gordon, Earl (Box 1)
    - Abinger, James Scarlett, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Acland, (Charles) Thomas Dyke (Box 1)
    - Acland, Thomas Dyke (Box 1)
    - Adams, Robert (Box 1)
    - Adams, William (Box 1)
    - Addington, J.N. (Box 1)
    - Agnew, Andrew, 7th Baronet (Box 1)
    - Airey, Richard (Box 1)
    - Allen, John (Box 1)
    - Allen, Joseph (Box 1)
    - Amherst, William Archer, 3rd Earl (Box 1)
    - Angell, James B. (Box 1)
    - Annesley, Arthur (Viscount Valentia and 1st Earl of Montnorris) (Box 1)
    - Arnold, Arthur (Box 1)
    - Ashburton, William Bingham Baring, 2nd Baron (Box 1)
    - Ashley, Evelyn (Box 1)
    - Asquith, Herbert Henry (Box 1)
    - Atcheson, Nathaniel (Box 1)
    - Azikiwe, Nnamdi (Box 1)
  - Argyll, George Douglas Campbell, 8th Duke, 1834-1876, (7 items) (Box 1)
  - Auckland, William George Eden, 1st Baron, and George Eden, 2nd Baron, 1799-1842, (7 items) (Box 1)
  - Back - Bourne, 1772-1887 and undated
    - Back, George (Box 1)
    - Backhouse, J. (Box 1)
    - Baden-Powell, George Smyth (Box 1)
    - Baily, Samuel (Box 1)
    - Baird, Andrew (Box 1)
    - Balfour, William (recipient) (Box 1)
    - Bamford, Samuel (Box 1)
    - Barger (?) (Box 1)
    - Baring, Charles Thomas (Box 1)
    - Baring, H. (Box 1)
    - Barker, Edward (Box 1)
    - Barrington, William Wildman, 2nd Viscount (Box 1)
    - Barry, Alfred (Box 1)
    - Bartlett, Ellis Ashmead (Box 1)
    - Bathhurst, Henry, 3rd Earl (Box 1)
    - Bathhurst, Henry, Archdeacon (Box 1)
    - Bayly, Robert (Box 1)
    - Beach, Michael Edward Hicks (Box 1)
    - Beauchamp, William Lygon, 1st Earl (Box 1)
    - Beaumont, Somerset (Box 1)
    - Beckett, Edmund, 5th Baronet (Box 1)
    - Bellamont, Earl (Box 1)
    - Benett, John (Box 1)
    - Bentham-Edwards, Matilda Barbara (Box 1)
    - Bentinck, George, Lord (Box 1)
    - Berekley, Francis Henry Fitzhardinge (Box 1)
    - Beresford, Charles William de la Poer, Baron (Box 1)
    - Berwick, William Noel Hill, 3rd Baron (Box 1)
    - Bloomfield, John Arthur Douglas, 2nd Baron (Box 1)
    - Blowitz, Henri Georges Stephane Adolphe Opper de (Box 1)
    - Bourchier (Box 1)
    - Bourne, William Sturges (Box 1)
  - Bramwell - Buxton, 1787-1930 and undated
    - Braconnier (see George I) (Box 1)
    - Bramwell, George William Wilshere Bramwell, Baron (Box 1)
    - Brassey, Thomas, 1st Earl (Box 1)
    - Bridport, Alexander Hood, 1st Viscount (Box 1)
    - Brooke, James, Raja of Sarawick (Box 1)
    - Brougham, Henry Peter (Baron Brougham and Vaux) (Box 1)
    - Broughton, Thomas Duer (Box 1)
    - Brown, George (Box 1)
    - Bruce, Thomas, 7th Earl of Elgin and 11th Earl of Kincardine (Box 1)
    - Buckingham (Richard Temple Nugent Brydges Chandos Grenville, 1st Duke of Buckingham and Chandos) (Box 1)
    - Buckinghamshire, Robert Hobart, 4th Earl (Box 1)
    - Buckle, George Earle (Box 1)
    - Buckle, Henry Thomas (Box 1)
    - Buller, Redvers Henry (Box 1)
    - Bulwer, W. Earle (Box 1)
    - Bunsen, Ernest (Box 1)
    - Burgess, Edward (Box 1)
    - Burgoyne, John Fox (Box 1)
    - Burlington, Lord (Box 1)
    - Burns, John Elliot (Box 1)
    - Butler, Henry Montagne (Box 1)
    - Buxton, Thomas Fowell, 3rd Baronet (Box 1)
  - Bradlaugh, Charles, 1868-1883 and undated, (10 items, some regarding a libel case) (Box 1)
  - Bright, John, 1857-1889, (17 items, including a printed copy of an 1851 speech entitled Papal Aggression) (Box 1)
  - Brownrigg, Robert, 1st Baronet, 1804-1838 and undated, (36 items, some regarding the Horseguards) (Box 1)
  - Burdett, Francis, 1809-1821, undated, (7 items) (Box 1)
  - Burt, Thomas, 1875-1891, (7 items) (Box 1)
  - Byles, W.P.(recipient), 1888-1892 and undated, (7 items) (Box 1)
  - Cadogan - Churchill, 1692-1930 and undated
    - Cadogan, George Henry, 5th Earl (Box 1)
    - Calcraft, John (Box 1)
    - Calvert, Harry (Box 1)
    - Camden, John Jeffries Pratt, 2nd Marquis (Box 1)
    - Campbell, Ilay (Box 1)
    - Campbell, Robert Calder (Box 1)
    - Cannon, Richard (Box 1)
    - Canterbury, Charles Manners Sutton, 1st Viscount (Box 1)
    - Cardonnel (Adam Mansfeldt de Cardonnel-Lawson) (Box 1)
    - Cardwell, Edward Cardwell, 1st Viscount (Box 1)
    - Carlisle, George William Frederick Howard, 7th Earl (Box 1)
    - Carter, Captain (Box 1)
    - Cavendish, Frederick (Box 1)
    - Cecil, Hugh Richard Heathcote Gascoyne, Baron Quickswood (Box 1)
    - Cecil, Robert Arthur James Gascoyne (Box 1)
    - Chadwick, Edward (?) (Box 1)
    - Chalmers, Robert (Box 1)
    - Chamberlain, Joseph Austen (Box 1)
    - Chatham, Edwin (Box 1)
    - Chesham, Edwin (Box 1)
    - Chester, Robert (Box 1)
    - Chichester, Bishop of (Box 1)
    - Childers, High Culling Eardley (Box 1)
    - Chisholm, A.W. (Box 1)
    - Churchill, Randolph (Box 1)
  - Clarke - Cowley, 1682-1906 and undated
    - Clarke, Edward (Box 1)
    - Clarkson, Thomas (Box 1)
    - Clay, James (Box 1)
    - Clay, W.L. (recipient) (Box 1)
    - Clifden, Henry Welbore, 2nd Viscount (Box 1)
    - Clifford, George (Box 1)
    - Clive, Edward, Lord (Box 1)
    - Clive, Robert (Box 1)
    - Clot-Bey (Box 1)
    - Cobbett, Susan (Box 1)
    - Cobbett, William (Box 1)
    - Cobden, Jane (Box 1)
    - Cobden, Richard (Box 1)
    - Coleridge, John Duke, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Coleridge, John Taylor (Box 1)
    - Collings, Jesse (Box 1)
    - Cotton, Charles (Box 1)
    - Courtin (Box 1)
    - Coutts, Burdett (Box 1)
    - Cowley (Box 1)
    - Cowley, Lord Henry Wellesley, Baron (Box 1)
  - Craig - Curzon, 1803-1972 and undated
    - Craig, James Henry (Box 1)
    - Cranborne (Box 1)
    - Crawford, G. (Box 1)
    - Crewe (Box 1)
    - Cromer, Evelyn Baring, 1st Earl (Box 1)
    - Crooke, Jeremiah (recipient) (Box 1)
    - Cross, Edith (Box 1)
    - Crothers, Robert (Box 1)
    - Cunningham, Robert (Box 1)
    - Curtis, William (Box 1)
    - Curzon of Kedleston, George Nathaniel, Marquess (Box 1)
  - Cambridge, Duke of 1871-1883, (8 items) (Box 1)
  - Canning, George, 1807-1856 and undated, (11 items, including a letter regarding Wellington's correspondence on the matter of a transport ship wrecked in the Tagus during his last Iberian campaign) (Box 1)
  - Clarendon, Earl of, 1856-1870 and undated, (7 items) (Box 1)
  - Croker, John Wilson, 1813-1830 and undated, (7 items, including Farquhar to Croker regarding a military surrender) (Box 1)
  - Dalhousie - Dey of Algiers, 1774-1914 and undated
    - Dalhousie, James Andrew Brown Ramsay, 10th Earl (Box 1)
    - Danby, Thomas (Box 1)
    - Dartmouth, William Legge, 2nd Earl (Box 1)
    - Darwin, Charles (autograph only) (Box 1)
    - Davers, Dr. (recipient) (Box 1)
    - Davids, Thomas William Rhys (Box 1)
    - Davis, John (Box 1)
    - Dawkins, Richard (Box 1)
    - Dawkins, William Boyd (Box 1)
    - Deare, M. (Box 1)
    - Dell, R. (Box 1)
    - Dempster, George (Box 1)
    - Devon, William Cavendish, 7th Duke (Box 1)
    - Devon, William Reginald Courtenay, 11th Earl (Box 1)
    - Dey of Algiers (Box 1)
  - Dillwyn - Dysart, 1798-1884 and undated
    - Dillwyn, Lewis Weston (Box 1)
    - Disraeli, B. (Disraeli, Benjamin, Earl of Beaconsfield) (Box 1)
    - Drake, Francis (Box 1)
    - Drummond, Charles (Box 1)
    - Drummond, Henry (Box 1)
    - Dublin, E. R. (Box 1)
    - Duckworth, John Thomas (Box 1)
    - Dudley, John William Ward, 1st Earl (Box 1)
    - Duff, Alexander (Box 1)
    - Dufferin, Ava Frederick Temple Hamilton-Temple, 1st Marquess (Box 1)
    - Duffy, Charles Gavin (Box 1)
    - Durham, George Frederick D'Arcy, 2nd Earl (Box 1)
    - Dyer, Samuel (Box 1)
    - Dysart, Wilberham, 6th Earl (Box 1)
  - Derby, Earls of, 1792-1918, (24 items) (Box 1)
  - Dumas, 1832-1852 and undated, (5 items) (Box 1)
  - Dundas, David, 1794-1855 and undated, (12 items, including two printed circulars from the War Office, 1804-05) (Box 1)
  - Durham, John George Lambton, 1st Earl, 1834-1839, (19 items) (Box 1)
  - Eden - Eyre, 1789-1908 and undated
    - Eden, William (recipient) (Box 1)
    - Elden, John Scott, 1st Earl (Box 1)
    - Ellenborough, Edward Law, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Ellis, Charles (Box 1)
    - Engleheart, George Herbert (Box 1)
    - Ernest (Box 1)
    - Erskine, Thomas Erskine, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Eversley (Box 1)
    - Eyre, Vincent (Box 1)
  - Ellis, George James Welbore Agar, 1807-1829 and undated, (6 items) (Box 1)
  - Fane - Fry, 1803-1908 and undated
    - Fane, Julian Henry Charles (Box 1)
    - Fawcett, Ralph (Box 1)
    - Fenwick, C. (Box 1)
    - Field, William (Box 1)
    - Fisher, John Arbuthnot, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Fitch, George (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald, A. (Box 1)
    - Fitzroy, George Henry (Box 1)
    - Fitzwilliam, Charles William Wentworth, 3rd Earl (Box 1)
    - Fletcher, J. (Box 1)
    - Flint, C.W. (Box 1)
    - Foster, Peter Le Neve (Box 1)
    - Fowler, Charles (Box 1)
    - Fortescue, William (Box 1)
    - Fox, Charles Richard (Box 1)
    - Fox, William Johnson (Box 1)
    - Freeman, Edward Augustus (Box 1)
    - Fry, Edmond (Box 1)
  - Foster, John, 1829 and undated, (3 items) (Box 1)
  - Gardner - Gough, 1709-1910 and undated
    - Gardner, Herbert (Box 1)
    - Geiger, Wilhelm George I/ Braconnier letters (Box 1)
    - Gibson, Thomas Milner (Box 1)
    - Gilby, Rev. (Box 1)
    - Gladstone, Herbert J. (Box 1)
    - Gladstone, William Henry (Box 1)
    - Gloucester, Duke of (Box 1)
    - Goad, Captain (Box 1)
    - Gordon, Adam (Box 1)
    - Gorst, John E. (Box 1)
    - Gough, Lord (Box 1)
  - Grafton - Grant, 1785-1894 and undated
    - Grafton, August Henry Fitzroy, Duke of (Box 1)
    - Graham, James (Box 1)
    - Grandprey, C. (Box 1)
    - Grant, Charles (Box 1)
    - Grant, Robert (Box 1)
  - Green - Guilford, 1832-1907 and undated
    - Green, J.R. (John Richard) (Box 1)
    - Gregory, William Henry (Box 1)
    - Gretton, Edward (Box 1)
    - Grey, Charles Edward (Box 1)
    - Grey, Thomas Philip, Earl (Box 1)
    - Grimston (Box 1)
    - Grosvenor, Richard (Box 1)
    - Guilford, Francis North, 4th Earl (Box 1)
  - Goschen, George Joachim, 1857-1896 and undated, (12 items) (Box 1)
  - Gosset, Charles, 1838 and undated, (12 items, including official correspondence with the Royal Navy and the War Office) (Box 1)
  - Goulburn, Henry, 1829-1855, (4 items) (Box 1)
  - Granville, Leveson Gower and George, 1st and 2nd Earls, 1812-1885 and undated, (19 items) (Box 1)
  - Hade - Hampden, 1799-1932 and undated
    - Hade, A. (?) (Box 1)
    - Hailey, Malcolm (Box 1)
    - Haldane, Richard (Box 1)
    - Hamilton, Alexander, 10th Duke (Box 1)
    - Hamilton, Charles (Box 1)
    - Hamley, Edward Bruce (Box 1)
    - Hamond, Andrew Snape, 1st Baronet (Box 1)
    - Hampden (Box 1)
  - Hardcastle - Hobhouse, 1741-1910 and undated
    - Hardcastle (Box 1)
    - Hargraves, A.B. (Box 1)
    - Harmer, Jason (Box 1)
    - Harrington, Charles Stanhope, 3rd Earl (Box 1)
    - Harvey, David Whittle (Box 1)
    - Hastings, Warren, Marquis (Box 1)
    - Hawkesbury, Charles Jenkinson, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Hawkins, Henry (Box 1)
    - Healy, Timothy Michael (Box 1)
    - Helmore, Katharine (Box 1)
    - Hemans, Felicia Dorothy (Box 1)
    - Henry, Mathew (Box 1)
    - Herbert, Auberon (Box 1)
    - Herschell, Farrer Herschell, 1st Baron (Box 1)
    - Higginson, Walter (Box 1)
    - Hirst, Francis Wrigley (Box 1)
    - Hobart, C.V.C. (Box 1)
    - Hobart, Robert, Baron (Box 1)
    - Hobhouse, Henry (Box 1)
    - Hobhouse, John (Box 1)
  - Holcroft - Hume, 1766-1881 and undated
    - Holcraft, Thomas (Box 1)
    - Holland, Lady (Box 1)
    - Holland, Lord (Box 1)
    - Hood, Samuel, 1st Baronet (Box 1)
    - Hope, Alexander James Beresford (Box 1)
    - Hope, James (Box 1)
    - Hopkins (Box 1)
    - Horsman, Edward (Box 1)
    - Hoste, D.W. (Box 1)
    - Howard, George (Box 1)
    - Howard, John (Box 1)
    - Howe, Lady Caroline (Box 1)
    - Howick, Charles Grey, Viscount (Box 1)
    - Hudson, James (Box 1)
    - Hughes, S. (Box 1)
    - Hume, David (Box 1)
    - Hume, William (Box 1)
  - Hunt - Hutt, 1556-1854 and undated
    - Hunt, Henry (Box 1)
    - Hunter, Thomas O. (Box 1)
    - Hutchinson, John Hely (Box 1)
    - Hutt, William (Box 1)
  - Harcourt, Leveson Vernon, 1887 and undated, ( 2 items) (Box 1)
  - Hay, John, 1857, ( 5 items) (Box 1)
  - Henry, George, 1887 and undated, (44 items, including correspondence related to Henry's mission in Nyasaland, two articles on Nyasaland and one on Malawi, and miscellany relating to Henry) (Box 1)
  - Hill, Richard, 1792-1819, (7 items) (Box 1)
  - Ingelow - Inglis, 1813-1871 and undated
    - Ingelow, Jean (Box 1)
    - Ingle, Thomas, Esq. (Box 1)
    - Inglis, Hugh (Box 1)
    - Inglis, John Eardley Wilmont (Box 1)
  - Jackson - Jones, 1764-1887 and undated
    - Jackson, Randle (Box 1)
    - James, Edward (recipient) (Box 1)
    - James, Robert (Box 1)
    - Jenkinson, Charles (Box 1)
    - Jesse, Edward (Box 1)
    - Jodrell, Fanny (Box 1)
    - Johnston, Alexander (Box 1)
    - Jones, John Gale (Box 1)
  - Kavanagh - Knight, 1842-1875 and undated
    - Kavanagh, Arthur MacMorrough (Box 1)
    - Kay, Lt. (?) (Box 1)
    - Kenyon (Box 1)
    - Keppel, Augustus (Box 1)
    - King, Yorke (?) (Box 1)
    - Kinghorne, W. (recipient) (Box 1)
    - Kingslake (?) (Box 1)
    - Kinnear (Box 1)
    - Kiwnaird, Arthur Fitzgerald (Box 1)
    - Klint (Box 1)
    - Knight, Charles (Box 1)
    - Knight, Richard (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, C.M., Esq., 1869-1875, (10 envelopes) (Box 1)
  - Labouchere - Latimer, 1674-1883 and undated (Box 2)
    - Labouchere, Henry Du Pré (Box 2)
    - Latimer (Box 2)
  - Lauderdale - Lees, 1762-1905 and undated
    - Lauderdale, James Maitland, 7th Earl (Box 2)
    - Laurence, French (Box 2)
    - Law, Andrew Bonar (Box 2)
    - Lawrence, Thomas (Box 2)
    - Layard, A.H., Esq. (envelopes only) (Box 2)
    - Leake, John Martin (Box 2)
    - Lee? (Box 2)
    - Leech, John (Box 2)
    - Lees, Elliott (Box 2)
  - Lefevre - Liston, 1776-1868 and undated
    - Lefevre, John Charles Shaw (Box 2)
    - Lennox, William (Box 2)
    - Leonard, H. (Box 2)
    - Letland (Box 2)
    - Leveson, Lord (Box 2)
    - Levi, Leone (Box 2)
    - Lewis, A. (Box 2)
    - Lewis, G.L. (Box 2)
    - Lincoln, Bishop of (Box 2)
    - Linden, C.J. (Box 2)
    - Lindsay, William Schaw (Box 2)
    - Liston, Robert (Box 2)
  - Lockhart - Lyttleton, 1783-1896 and undated
    - Lockhart (Box 2)
    - Lockwood, Amelius Mark Richard (Box 2)
    - Lockwood, Frank (Box 2)
    - Longford, Edward Michael Pakenham, 1st Earl (Box 2)
    - Lourence, Abbot (Box 2)
    - Lowther, James (Box 2)
    - Lubbock, J. (Box 2)
    - Lugard, Frederick John Dealtry, Baron (Box 2)
    - Lumley, William (Box 2)
    - Lylton (Box 2)
    - Lyndhurst, John Singelton Copeley, 1st Baron (Box 2)
    - Lyon, George (Box 2)
    - Lyttleton (Box 2)
  - Lansdowne, Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquess, 1825-1842 and undated, (8 items) (Box 2)
  - Lecky, William Edward Harpole, 1881-1899, (7 items) (Box 2)
  - Lenty, John, Captain, 1857, (6 items, some in oversize folder, all relating to the cargo ship Sea Witch) (Box 2)
  - Liverpool, Charles Jenkinson, 1st Earl, 1787-1818, (5 items) (Box 2)
  - Lucan, George Charles Bingham, 3rd Earl, 1830-1888 and undated, (7 items, including November 1888 obituary clipped from the Times, an engraving of Lucan, and a printed account of his life and military career) (Box 2)
  - Macaulay - McCoan, 1700-1927 and undated
    - Macaulay, Zachary (Box 2)
    - MacDonagh, Michael (Box 2)
    - MacDonald, Ramsay (Box 2)
    - Maclean, Harry (Box 2)
    - Macmillian, Harold (Box 2)
    - Macpherson, John Macpherson, 1st Baronet (Box 2)
    - Maine, Henry James Sumner (?) (Box 2)
    - Makintosh, James (Box 2)
    - Malcolm, John (Box 2)
    - Malet, Edward (Box 2)
    - Manchester, Charles Mountague, Duke (Box 2)
    - Mandeville (Box 2)
    - Manners, John (Box 2)
    - Manners, Robert, Lord (Box 2)
    - Manning, Henry Edward (Box 2)
    - Mansfield, William Murray, 1st Earl (Box 2)
    - Mayne, James (Box 2)
    - McCarthy, Justin (Box 2)
    - McCoan, James Carlile (Box 2)
  - Merry - Miall, 1838-1876 and undated
    - Merry, W. (Box 2)
    - Metcalfe, Charles Theophilus (recipient) (Box 2)
    - Metford, William Ellis (Box 2)
    - Metternich (Box 2)
    - Miall, Edward (Box 2)
  - Minto - Murrell, 1786-1915 and undated
    - Minto, Gilbert Elliot, 2nd Earl (Box 2)
    - Mitford, Algernon Bertram Freeman (Box 2)
    - Miyatovic, Cheddo (Box 2)
    - Molesworth, William (Box 2)
    - Monat, Frederick J. (Box 2)
    - Montagu, Robert, 3rd Earl (Box 2)
    - Morel, E. D. (Edmund Dene), 1873-1924 (Box 2)
    - Morfell (Box 2)
    - Morley, Arnold (Box 2)
    - Morley, John (Box 2)
    - Morley, Samuel (Box 2)
    - Mornington, Wellesley, Earl (Box 2)
    - Morton, E. J. C. (Box 2)
    - Mount-Edgcumbe, Richard, 2nd Earl (Box 2)
    - Mountford, Joseph (Box 2)
    - Mulgrave (Box 2)
    - Mundella, Anthony John (Box 2)
    - Munro, J. Spens (Box 2)
    - Murray, John (Box 2)
    - Murrell (Box 2)
  - Marsden-Smedley, 1910-1911 and undated, (10 items, including correspondence regarding Marsden-Smedley's unsuccessful run for Parliament in 1910) (Box 2)